<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-mbci-ippm-ioam-template-option-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Fixed IOAM Option">In Situ Operations, Administration, and Maintenance (IOAM) Template Option</title>

    <author fullname="Tal Mizrahi" initials="T." surname="Mizrahi">
      <organization abbrev="">Huawei</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Matam</street>

          <city>Haifa</city>

          <code>3190501</code>

          <country>Israel</country>
        </postal>

        <email>tal.mizrahi.phd@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Frank Brockners" initials="F." surname="Brockners">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Hansaallee 249, 3rd Floor</street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <city>DUESSELDORF</city>

          <code>40549</code>

          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>

        <email>fbrockne@cisco.com</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="A." surname="Clemm" fullname="Alexander Clemm">
      <organization>Sympotech</organization>
      <address>
        <email>ludwig@clemm.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Justin Iurman" initials="J." surname="Iurman">
      <organization abbrev="">University of Liege</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>10, Allee de la decouverte (B28)</street>

          <code>4000</code>

          <city>Sart-Tilman</city>

          <country>Belgium</country>
        </postal>

        <email>justin.iurman@uliege.be</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Shwetha Bhandari" initials="S." surname="Bhandari">
      <organization abbrev="">Databricks</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Angkor West Building Bagmane Capital Tech Park Ferns City Doddanekkundi</street>

          <city>Mahadevpura Bengaluru, Karnataka 560048</city>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>shwetha.bhandari@databricks.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Tianran Zhou" initials="T." surname="Zhou">
      <organization abbrev="">Huawei</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>156 Beiqing Rd.</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <code>100095</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>zhoutianran@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
	  
    <date year="2025"/>

    <area>OPS</area>

    <workgroup>IPPM</workgroup>

    <keyword>IOAM</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>In situ measurement is performed by incorporating performance related 
	  information into in-flight data packets. This document specifies a 
	  new IOAM Option-Type that has a fixed length and can be updated by
	  transit nodes along the path. It enables lightweight monitoring using constant-length 
	  data that is not changed in-flight and is not affected by the number of hops in the network.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
	  <t>In Situ Operations, Administration, and Maintenance (IOAM) 
	  <xref target="RFC9197"/> is used for measuring and monitoring a network
	  by incorporating measurement and operational data into some or all of
	  the data packets. <xref target="RFC9197"/> has defined several
	  Option-Types, intended for different purposes.</t>

	  <t>This document introduces a new IOAM Option-Type that can be 
	  incorporated into data packets and updated by transit
	  nodes along the path. Compared to existing IOAM Trace Option-Types, the 
	  new Option-Type provides performance information using 
	  data fields that have a constant length.</t>
	  
	  <t>There are several in-progress proposals that use a fixed-size
	  telemetry header, including <xref target="I-D.cxx-ippm-ioamaggr"/>, 
	  <xref target="I-D.mzbc-ippm-transit-measurement-option"/>,
	  <xref target="I-D.xiao-ippm-ioam-trace-extensions"/>,
	  <xref target="I-D.filsfils-ippm-path-tracing"/>,
	  <xref target="I-D.ravi-ippm-csig"/>, and
	  <xref target="I-D.shi-ippm-congestion-measurement-data"/>.
	  These proposals can potentially benefit from the IOAM Option-Type that is
	  presented in this document.</t>
	  

    </section>

    <section anchor="Conventions" title="Conventions">
      <section title="Requirement Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
        "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP
        14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only
        when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Terminology">
	  
        <t>Abbreviations used in this document:</t>

        <t><list hangIndent="11" style="hanging">
            <t hangText="IOAM:">In-situ Operations, Administration, and
            Maintenance</t>

            <t hangText="OAM:">Operations, Administration, and Maintenance</t>

          </list></t>

	    <t>The terms Option-Type, encapsulating 
		node, decapsulating node, and transit node are defined in 
		<xref target="RFC9197"/>.</t>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="useSec" title="Use Cases">
      <t>There is a set of use cases that the current IOAM Option-Types do not 
      support. This section lists a set of use cases for the IOAM Template 
      Option-Type.</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Aggregated information: aggregated information across several 
          nodes, e.g., <xref target="I-D.cxx-ippm-ioamaggr"/>. Many 
          applications interested in telemetry data across a path are not
          focused on individual node's telemetry, but on an aggregated metric
          that can provide a more holistic picture. Aggregating IOAM data 
          along a network path meets this requirement. IOAM nodes do not only 
          retrieve information, but also perform functions such as sum, 
          average, minimum, or maximum of a given data parameter and carry the 
          result to the next IOAM node in an IOAM data field.</t>

          <t>Congestion information: information relating to the congestion
          status can be collected from nodes along the path, e.g., 
          <xref target="I-D.ravi-ippm-csig"/> providing a finer level of
          granularity than conventional ECN while limiting the congestion
          status to a fixed size.</t>

          <t>Combined information: a combination of aggregated information
          and congestion-related information can be collected along the path,
          e.g., <xref target="I-D.mzbc-ippm-transit-measurement-option"/>,
          while using a fixed size.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="reqSec" title="Requirements for the IOAM Template Option-Type">
      <t>This section lists requirements for the IOAM Template Option-Type:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Templates supported MUST have a fixed length and fixed structure. 
          Fixed length and structure are to simplify parsing of the 
          Option-Type.</t>

          <t>Each templates is a composition of one or more data fields.</t>

          <t>Data fields within a template can have different sizes (e.g., 8 
          bits, 16 bits, 32 bits).</t>

          <t>Templates MUST align to 4 octet boundaries. If necessary, 
          padding fields are used to guarantee 4-octet alignment.</t>

          <t>Data fields within a Template can be read-only for IOAM nodes or 
          read-write for IOAM nodes, depending on their use.</t>

          <t>The IOAM Template Option-Type SHOULD support IETF defined (IANA 
          registry) Templates for use-cases which are defined by the IETF as 
          well as custom/deployment specific templates, that are defined by 
          the operator and are specific to a deployment.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="option" title="In situ Template Option-Type">
      <t>This document defines a new IOAM Option-Type, the
	  Template Option-Type. The length of the Template 
	  Option-Type MUST NOT be modified by IOAM transit nodes.
	  However, IOAM transit nodes MAY modify the option data
	  in the Template Option-Type.
	  <xref target="FixedFormat"/> presents the
	  format of this Option-Type.</t>

          <figure align="center" anchor="FixedFormat"
                  title="Template Option-Type">
            <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
         
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |        Namespace-ID           |  Template-ID  |    Length     |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                                                               |
   ~       Template-Data depending on the Template-ID value        ~
   |                                                               |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   
           ]]></artwork>
          </figure>

      <t>
	     An IOAM node that complies to this draft MUST support the following
		 fields, as depicted in <xref target="FixedFormat"/>:
		 
	<list style="hanging">
	<t hangText="Namespace-ID:">A 16-bit namespace identifier, as 
		   defined in <xref target="RFC9197"/>.</t>

        <t hangText="Template-ID:">An 8-bit identifier that specifies 
		 the template that follows. A new 
		 registry is defined for this field, as specified in 
		 <xref target="IANA"/>. The value 0 has been assigned, 
		 indicating "No Option Data". 
		 Assignments of values 1 to 127 are controlled by IANA.
		 Values 128 to 255 are can be defined by an operator for a 
		 specific deployment.</t>

	 <t hangText="Length:">An 8-bit length that specifies the size of 
		 the Template-Data in multiples of 4 octets.</t>

	 <t hangText="Template-Data:">The data that follows the 
		 Template-ID has a constant length. The semantics and length 
		 of the data are determined by the Template-ID. The option 
		 data might consist of more than one sub-field.</t>
          </list></t>

	  <t>The specification of the Template-ID values and the
	  corresponding option data formats is outside the scope of this
	  document.</t>
	    
	  <t>As in <xref target="RFC9197"/>, the Template Option-Type can
          be incorporated into all or a subset of the traffic that is forwarded
          by the encapsulating node. Notably, this option adds a fixed and 
	  low overhead to data packets, which remains constant along the path.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="exampleSec" title="Examples">
        <t>The section lists examples of how the template option can be used.
        </t>

    <section title="IOAM Data Aggregation Along The Path">
        <t><xref target="I-D.cxx-ippm-ioamaggr"/> describes use cases to 
        aggregate IOAM data along a network path.  Rather than just 
        collecting data at IOAM nodes, data is collected and processed by 
        the IOAM nodes - using functions like sum, average, minimum, or 
        maximum of a given data parameter - and the result stored in a 
        data field called "Aggregate" (see below). The Template Option 
        can be used to support this use-case with the following example 
        template:</t>

          <figure align="center" anchor="aggrFigure"
                  title="Aggregation Template">
            <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
         
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |        Namespace-ID           |  TBD_1        |   Length=2    |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |               IOAM Data Param                 |  Aggregator   |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                           Aggregate                           |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   
           ]]></artwork>
          </figure>

	<t><list style="hanging">
	<t hangText="IOAM Data Param:">This field identifies the data parameter that is
        to be aggregated across the nodes.  It MUST be set by the IOAM
        encapsulating node.  IOAM transit nodes MUST NOT change it.</t>

        <t hangText="Aggregator:">This 8-bit field identifies the aggregation function
        that is to be applied.  Its value MUST be set by the IOAM
        encapsulating node.  IOAM transit nodes MUST not change it.  The
        following aggregators are defined: Sum, Min, Max, Average.</t>

	 <t hangText="Aggregate:">This 32-bit field contains the aggregated value.  Its
        value is initialized by the encapsulating node,in general by
        simply recording the value of its data parameter that is to be
        aggregated.  The field is updated by each subsequent node pre the
        requested aggregation, including IOAM transit nodes as well as the
        IOAM decapsulating node (prior to performing decapsulation).</t>

          </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Transit Measurement Template">
        <t>The use case that is presented in
        <xref target="I-D.mzbc-ippm-transit-measurement-option"/> provides 
        aggregated transit delay information, as well as congestion status 
        of transit nodes, as shown in the following template:</t> 

          <figure align="center" anchor="transitFigure"
                  title="Transit Measurement Template">
            <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
         
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |        Namespace-ID           |  TBD_2        |   Length=2    |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                       Accumulated Delay                       |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |   Hop Count   |            Status Bitmap                      |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   
           ]]></artwork>
          </figure>

	<t><list style="hanging">
	<t hangText="Accumulated Delay:">represents the sum of the transit delay values in
        nanoseconds along the path of the packet, including the current
        node.</t>

        <t hangText="Hop Count/Status Bitmap:">indicates the devices along the path that
        have experienced congestion. Hop Count is a one-octet field that indicates the number of hops
        since the encapsulating node, and is updated by each transit node. Status Bitmap 
        is a three octet field that represents the congestion
        status of each transit node along the path.  The value '1'
        indicates that the current packet was enqueued in a queue that
        is congested.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>


    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
        <t>To be added to a future version of this document.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The security considerations of IOAM in general are discussed in 
	  <xref target="RFC9197"/>. The Template Option-Type may be used for reconnaissance, which
	  in turn can facilitate other types of attacks. As in other types of IOAM
	  data fields, a malicious attacker can manipulate the field 
	  values in order to create a false illusion of nonexistent network issues 
	  or prevent the detection of actual ones.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.9197'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.cxx-ippm-ioamaggr'?>
	  
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.mzbc-ippm-transit-measurement-option'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.xiao-ippm-ioam-trace-extensions'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.filsfils-ippm-path-tracing'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ravi-ippm-csig'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.shi-ippm-congestion-measurement-data'?>
    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
